Guide to the Rosemary Trump Papers, 1950-2005 AIS.2005.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rosemary Trump Papers
1950-2005
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Trump, Rosemary T.
AIS.2005.04
43.75 Linear Feet (25 boxes)
Born August 23, 1944, Rosemary Trump dedicated much of her life to the labor movement. Among many positions, Trump served on the executive board of the Service Employees International Union and held the presidency of Local 58 (Blawnox, Pennsylvania) for twenty seven years. Her belief that unions should improve society as well as benefiting the economic condition of union members caused her to be involved in many activities. She was active politically, especially in Westmoreland County, and served as a delegate to every Democratic National Convention from 1984-2004. In addition, Trump sought to help maintain Pittsburgh's cultural identity by participating in organizations which aimed to preserve labor history, protect public television, or strengthen ties between religious and labor leaders. This collection dates from 1950-2004 and includes personal and professional materials on subjects including her labor union career, political activism, community activism, preserving labor history, labor and religion, and advocacy for Women. The collection consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings, articles, meeting minutes, memoranda, reports, resolutions, leaflets, applications, membership cards, speeches, proceedings and financial statements. The collection also contains photographs and oversized materials such as awards and scrapbooks.
Biography
Rosemary Trump (nee Hugh) was born August 23, 1944 in Fairchance, Pennsylvania. In her youth, Trump actively participated in the Girl Scouts of America and student council. In 1962, she graduated from Fairchance-Georges Joint Senior High School and enrolled at the American University in Washington D.C. In 1966, Trump graduated from the School of Government and Public Administration at American University with a Bachelor of Arts degree. In 1967, she married Thomas Reed Trump, and the couple moved to Boston, where she became a social worker for the City of Boston's Welfare Department. Frustrated with her working conditions, Trump decided to help organize her colleagues. This initial organizing work led the Service Employees International Union (SEIU) Local 509 to hire her in 1969 as a full-time organizer of Massachusetts welfare workers. In 1970, the couple moved back to the Pittsburgh area, where Rosemary Trump continued working as an SEIU organizer and assisted in the development of Pennsylvania Social Services Union Local 668 and SEIU Local 585. After spending several months as an appointed trustee for SEIU Local 585, she was elected president of the local in September 1973.
During the 1970s and into the early 1990s, Trump's activity within the labor movement expanded greatly. The Pennsylvania State Council formed in 1974, and Trump was selected as its first secretary-treasurer. Also in 1974 Trump became a member of the SEIU International Executive Board. In 1975, the SEIU Eastern Conference elected Trump recording secretary, a position she held until 1986 when she became the Conference's vice president. In October 1978, the Western Pennsylvania Area Food Beverage Trades Council elected Trump recording secretary. In 1980, Trump became SEIU's first female International Vice President. In 1990 she participated in a Jewish Labor Committee tour of Israel. In 1992-1993 Trump traveled overseas once again to Geneva, Switzerland where she served as an American delegate to the International Labor Organization's session on part-time work. In 1995, Trump became a vice president of the Pennsylvania AFL-CIO. Despite her prominence in the national labor movement, Trump lost her presidency of Local 585 to James Neville in 2000. As a result, Trump also lost her SEIU international vice presidency. Left with no direct contact to the SEIU, Trump became a commentator on the labor movement and participated mostly in local labor councils.
In addition to being highly active in the labor movement, Rosemary Trump participated extensively in the community and politics. As of 1974, she served as a charter member of the Pennsylvania Labor History Society. Starting in the 1970s Trump also held memberships in the American Civil Liberties Union, Coalition of Labor Union Women, National Organization for Women, and National Women's Political Caucus. Beginning in the 1980s, Trump added memberships in the Americans for Democratic Action, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and Peace Links. Rosemary Trump was a charter member of the Steel Industry Heritage Corporation (SIHC) and has served as an executive board member since 1992. In conjunction with her SIHC membership, Trump joined several other labor history organizations, which advocated the establishment of the Rivers of Steel Heritage Area. Trump's other community interests included the struggle to preserve non-commercialized public television in Pittsburgh and efforts to foster a more cooperative relationship between religion and labor to help advocate for better economic conditions. Trump's political activity led members of the Westmoreland County Democratic Party to elect her chair of the organization in 2002. Trump served as a delegate to every Democratic National Convention held from 1984-2004 and was chosen as an elector in the 2004 Pennsylvania Electoral College.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection dates from 1950-2004 and is separated into seven series: Series I Personal, Series II Labor Union Career, Series III Political Activism, Series IV Community Activism, Series V Preserving Labor History, Series VI Labor and Religion, and Series VII Advocacy for Women. The collection consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings, articles, meeting minutes, memoranda, reports, resolutions, leaflets, applications, membership cards, speeches, proceedings and financial statements. The collection also contains photographs and oversized materials such as awards and scrapbooks,which are stored in a separate area. Although some files from the closely related collection of Records of SEIU Local 585 (AIS 198214) have been incorporated into this collection, the papers from her presidency of SEIU Local 585, which are essential for developing a complete portrait of Trump's labor career, remain with the Local's records. Additional scope notes are provided at the series and subseries level.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions
Acquisition Information
Gift of Rosemary Trump, 1982, 1985, 1989, 2003, and 2005.
Previous Citation
Rosemary Trump Papers, 1950-2005, AIS.2005.04, Archives Service Center, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh
Papers of Rosemary Trump, 1950-2005, UE/Labor 2005:04, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Labor; Labor unions -- Political activity -- Pennsylvania; Social action; Labor unions -- Pennsylvania; Women; AFL-CIO. International Affairs Department; Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.); Democratic Party (Pa.); Pennsylvania Labor History Society; Pennsylvania Social Services Union. Local 668 (Harrisburg, Pa.); Service Employees International Union. Local 585 (Blawnox, Pa.); Steel Industry Heritage Corporation; Trump, Rosemary T.
- Personal, 1950-2004; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I is arranged chronologically and subdivided into: Youth and Adulthood. Dating from 1950-1966, the youth files are arranged alphabetically and outline Trump's life before her college graduation. Several files focus on her activities as a Girl Scout and student council member. Dating from 1967-2004, the adulthood files document the personal aspects of Rosemary Trump's life as she began and expanded her career as a labor advocate and community activist. In addition to documenting her personal life, a few files reveal Trump's activities as a Boston area social worker in the late 1960s.
  - Youth and College, 1.
    - Awards and Certificates, 1954-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence- Incoming, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2-11)
    - Correspondence- Outgoing, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 12-18)
    - Civil Service Commission Information, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Girl Scouts of America Camp, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Papers, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - Report Cards and Transcripts, 1950-1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Research on Public Transportation, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Student Council Conference, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
    - Washington Seminar, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Photo Album, 1950s-60s (Box 1, Folder Oversized)
    - Scrapbook, 1950s-60s (Box 1, Folder Oversized)
  - Adulthood, 2.
    - Awards/Certificates, 1997-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Incoming, 1967-2004 (Box 2, Folder 2-15)
    - Date books/Schedules, 1987-2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Membership Cards, 1970s-90s (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1986-2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Social Work- Articles, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Social Work- General, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Speeches, 1977-1999 (Box 2, Folder 22-25)
    - Surveys, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Labor Union Career, 1969-2004; II.
  Series II consists of materials Rosemary Trump amassed while serving in various posts of the Service Employee International Union (SEIU). Divided into six subseries: Local 509, Local 585, Local 668, Pennsylvania State Council, Eastern Conference, SEIU International and AFL-CIO, the arrangement illustrates how Trump's localized activities provided a springboard for her participation in international entities.
  - Local 509 (Boston, Massachusetts), 1968-1976; 1.
    Scope and Contents note
    Subseries I. documents Rosemary Trump's actions as an organizer as well as the progress of the Local 509. Although Trump only worked for local from 1969-1970, the records date from 1968-1976.
    - General, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - History, 1968-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Local 509 News, 1969-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Research- Massachusetts Public Welfare, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Research- National Federation of Social Service Employees, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Research- New York City Material - SSEU, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Local 585 (Blawnox, Pennsylvania), 1970-2001; 2.
    Subseries II. contains files from Local 585, which began in 1969 and operated until 2000 when it membership was transferred to three industry-specific locals. Rosemary Trump served as its president from 1973-2000 and her papers from that office are located in the Records of Local 585. Instead of documenting her presidency, this subseries provides excellent insight into Trump's earliest duties as an organizer and trustee of Local 585 (1970-1973) as well as the local's final presidential election in 2000.
    - Activity Reports, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence- Other State Welfare Departments, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence- Pennsylvania Welfare Department, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence- SEIU, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Election Protest- Campaign Materials, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Election Protest- Charges Against James Neville, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Election Protest- Evidence Against James Neville, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Election Protest- Guidelines to Challenging Local Elections, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Election Protest- Hearing on Charges Against James Neville, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Election Protest- Memos From James Neville, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Election Protest, Monitor 585 Committee- Monitor 585 Committee- Petition, no date (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Election Protest, Monitor 585 Committee- Newsletter, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Election Protest- Support Letters, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Election Protest- Trump's Protest of Election and Discharge, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Memos to SEIU, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Newsletters- Miscellaneous, 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Newsletters- Welfare Scene, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Research- Act 195, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Research- AFSCME Literature, no date (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Research- Welfare Bills, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Time Cards, 1975-1996 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Local 668 (Harrisburg, Pennsylvania), 1970s; 3.
    Subseries III. dates from the 1970s and documents Trump's participation in Local 668's initial development.
    - Flyers, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - General, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Pennsylvania State Council, 1974-1999; 4.
    Subseries IV. contains Trump's files from her position as the council's secretary-treasurer, 1974-1999. In general, these files document the business of the council, as well as the planning and implementation of meetings, events and conventions.
    - 1199 Contract, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Convention- Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - Convention- General, 1974-1986 (Box 4, Folder 4-11)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1986 (Box 4, Folder 12-20)
    - Executive Board Meetings, 1974-1999 (Box 4, Folder 21-29)
    - Finances, 1975-1999 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Luncheon for Bob Edgar, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Member Lists, 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Perkins, Jane, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Time Cards, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Eastern Conference, 1980-1986; 5.
    Subseries V. is arranged chronologically. The files provide insight into topics explored at the conventions held by the Eastern Conference, which contained SEIU locals from Maine to Florida.
    - Conventions, 1980-1986 (Box 5, Folder 6-10)
  - SEIU International, 1974-2001; 6.
    Series VI. documents Trump's activities in the SEIU, which was established in 1921 as the Building Service Employees International Union and currently represents workers in the health care industry, public employees, building service workers, and industrial and allied workers in the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico. Arranged alphabetically, the SEIU subseries is subdivided as follows: Conventions, Executive Board, General Files and International Affairs Committee. The conventions files date from 1980-2000 and contain specific files for committees, reports, and resolutions, as well as miscellaneous files that consist of materials distributed to delegates. Dating from 1974-2000, the executive board files contain materials utilized by board members in preparation for and during international executive board meetings. In addition to meeting materials, the "votes" folders contain forms mailed-in or faxed by Trump for issues not resolved at meetings. The general files date from 1979-2001 and are arranged alphabetically by folder title. Many of the files are from conferences, councils, committees and meetings developed by the SEIU to resolve specific issues or create cooperation between groups with similar objectives. The New Strength and New Unity folders contain campaign platforms utilized by SEIU presidential candidates. Finally, the International Affairs Committee files date from 1978-1995 and describe the condition of workers across the globe, as well as the impact of globalized trade. Many files examine the plight of workers in Central America and the Philippines, as well as their impact on the global economy. While most of the files originated in International Affairs Committee meetings, a few files document Trump's participation in a Jewish Labor Committee-sponsored tour of Israel (1990) and the International Labor Conference in Geneva (1992-1993).
    - Conventions, 1980-2000
      - Committee on Women in the Labor Force, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Constitutional Amendments, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Local Autonomy Issue, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Miscellaneous, 1980-2000 (Box 5, Folder 14-19)
      - Office Worker Division Meeting, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Reports, 1988-1992 (Box 5, Folder 21-24)
      - Reports, 1996-2000 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
      - Resolutions, 1988-2000 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
    - Executive Board
      - Bold Action, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Convention Planning, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1974-2000 (Box 6, Folder 11-16)
      - Healthcare, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Meeting Materials, 1989-1994 (Box 6, Folder 18-20)
      - Meeting Materials, 1995-1999 (Box 7, Folder 1-15)
      - Meeting Materials, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 1-15)
      - Miscellaneous, 1987-1991 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
      - Political Committee, 1998-1999 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Private Capital Presentation by ULLICO, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Reports, 1981-1991 (Box 9, Folder 5-14)
      - Resolutions, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Votes, 1994-2000 (Box 9, Folder 16-17)
    - General Files
      - Activity Reports, 1979-1993 (Box 10, Folder 1-13)
      - Clerical Division Meeting, 1982-1988 (Box 10, Folder 14-15)
      - Committee on the Future - A New Voice for SEIU Members, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - Conference on Legislative and Political Action, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - Democratic National Convention, 1988, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 18)
      - Directory, no date (Box 10, Folder 19)
      - Finance Committee, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 20)
      - Finances, 1997-2001 (Box 10, Folder 21-23)
      - Grassroots Organizing, 1998-2000 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Legislative Conference, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1988-2001 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
      - New Strength Unity Plan, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - New Voices Campaign, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Office Worker Division Meeting, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
      - Organizing Workforce 2000, no date (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Pay Inequities, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Planning Documents, 1986-1987 (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
      - Political Committee Meeting, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Political Correspondence, 1981-1984 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - Presidents Committee 2000 Summaries, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Public Division Board Meeting, 1998-2000 (Box 11, Folder 16-18)
      - Public Division Convention, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 19-21)
      - SEIU Fund Trustees Meeting, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 22-23)
      - SEIU Update, 1989-1991 (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - State Council, 1998-2000 (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
      - Working Capital Seminar, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - International Affairs Committee
      - Bulletin, 1988-1989 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Canada Trade Issues, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Central America - Labor and World Economy, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 12, Folder 9-12)
      - El Salvador-General, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - El Salvador-Labor Rights, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - El Salvador-National Debate for Peace, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - El Salvador-Sourcebook, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - El Salvador Trade, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - International Labor Conference- General, 1993-1994 (Box 12, Folder 18-19)
      - International Labor Conference- Part-Time Workers, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 20-21)
      - Journal Articles, 1988-1989 (Box 12, Folder 22-23)
      - Labor in Israel, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Leaflets and Press Releases, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Meeting Materials, 1988-1995 (Box 13, Folder 3-8)
      - Memoranda and Appendix, 1987-1988 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1981-1993 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Newsletters, 1988-1990 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Newspaper Articles, 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Nicaragua - Sourcebook, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Peace and Friendship, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Philippines- Articles, 1987-1990 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Philippines- Political Unionism, Development and Democratization, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 16-17)
      - Philippines- US-Sponsored Low-Intensity Conflict, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 19-22)
      - Resolutions and Agendas, 1988-1989 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Seminar on Swedish Labor Market, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - SEIU/STISSS Background Material, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - AFL-CIO, 1979-2004; 7.
    Subseries VII. is separated into national materials and Pennsylvania materials. The national files date from 1979-1999, are arranged alphabetically, and contain materials given to delegates during AFL-CIO conferences and conventions. The Pennsylvania files date from 1992-2004 and document the activities of PA AFL-CIO conventions, conferences and executive council meetings.
    - National Conference-CLC Best Practices, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - National Conference-Elected Leader Task Force, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - National Conference-Public Employee Department, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - National Conference-State and Local Council, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - National Convention- Amendments and Resolutions, 1995, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
    - National Convention- Capital Stewardship, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - National Convention- Executive Council Report, 1995, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 11-12)
    - National Convention- Miscellaneous, 1995, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
    - National Convention- Planning Committee, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 15-16)
    - National Convention- SEIU Caucus Meeting, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Pennsylvania Conference-Organizing Communities, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Pennsylvania Conference-Legislative, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Pennsylvania Convention- Correspondence, 1998-2002 (Box 15, Folder 12-14)
    - Pennsylvania Convention- Executive Council Meeting, 1997-2000 (Box 15, Folder 15-21)
- Political Activism, 1982-2004; III.
  Series III contains information on political campaigns, elections, and conventions. It is broken into two categories: National and Pennsylvania. The national files date from 1982-2004 and focuses on Democratic National Conventions attended by Rosemary Trump. The convention materials are arranged chronologically and mainly consist of correspondence, convention handouts, reports, summaries and proceedings. The Pennsylvania files date from 1991-2004 and contain information on political campaigns for governor, senator, congressional representative and local offices in Southwest Pennsylvania, as well as presidential campaigns. The strongest component of this series is the Westmoreland County Democratic Party files, which is especially important after 2000 when Trump became more involved in the organization.
  - National, 1.
    - AFL-CIO Women Working for 84, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Democratic National Committee Guides, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- Correspondence, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- General, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- Convention Guides, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- Correspondence, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 6-7)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- Delegate Information, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- Handouts - Miscellaneous, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- Handouts - Official, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- Miscellaneous, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- Official Proceedings, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Democratic National Party Convention- General, 1988-2004 (Box 16, Folder 13-17)
    - National-House Democratic Caucus, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Political Labor School, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 19)